<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preacht upon the death of Mrs. Anne Barnardiston (daughter of Nathanael Barnardiston, Esq., late of Hackney) who departed this life the 30th day of Decemb. 1681, at the age of seventeen with a brief account of some remarkable passages of her life and death.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5070</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12898794</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12898794</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95216</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60155)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95216)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 728:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preacht upon the death of Mrs. Anne Barnardiston (daughter of Nathanael Barnardiston, Esq., late of Hackney) who departed this life the 30th day of Decemb. 1681, at the age of seventeen with a brief account of some remarkable passages of her life and death.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.A. for B. Alsop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: John Shower.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barnardiston, Anne, 1664-1681.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHT Upon the DEATH OF M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>ANNE BARNARDISTON,</hi> (DAUGHTER of <hi>NATHANAEL BARNARDISTON</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> late of <hi>Hackney:</hi>) Who departed this Life the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1681. at the Age of Seventeen.</p>
            <p>With a brief Account of ſome Remarkable Paſſages of her LIFE and DEATH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Deſire of her Relations.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 103.15.</hi>
                  </bibl> As for man his dayes are as graſs: as a flower of the field ſo he flouriſheth.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 16.</hi>
                  </bibl> For the wind paſſeth over it, and it is gone, and the place thereof ſhall know it no more.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. A.</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Alſop</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Bible,</hi> and <hi>John Dunton</hi> at the <hi>Black Raven,</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO The Much Honoured, MADAM <hi>ELIZABETH BARNARDISTON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſad Occaſion of the <hi>Sermon,</hi> and your Relation to <hi>Her,</hi> whoſe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing requeſt was fulfilled in my preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>it,</hi> doth ſtyle the Dedication yours. Though what I have mention'd of your excellent <hi>Daughter,</hi> is leſs than others would have ſaid on the ſame ſubject, yet having given an account of her preparedneſs and willingneſs to dye, methinks that ſhould be conſidered as a ſufficient Argument to mitigate your Sorrow, and prevent its exceſs.<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 13.</note> 'Tis the Apoſtles Inſtruction <hi>concerning them who ſleep in Jeſus,</hi> that <hi>we ought not to ſorrow as do others, who have no hope.</hi> Such were the <hi>Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians;</hi> and 'tis obſerv'd of them, that <hi>they</hi> mourned longer for the death of old <hi>Jacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 50.3</note> than his own Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> did. I know the <hi>Time of Her Death</hi> gives an Accent to the Calamity: That before your Mourning Weeds were laid aſide for one of <hi>the beſt of Husbands, who hath a good Report of all
<pb facs="tcp:95216:3"/> men, and of the Truth it ſelf;</hi> you ſhould be forced to continue the ſame, or put on more, for the <hi>Loſs</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> a Child, in the <hi>Prime</hi> of her Youth, and Strength, and Beauty: <hi>A Loſs</hi> for which you do not mourn alone, ſince many others are partners of your grief; not by ſympathy only as pitying you, but from a due Reſpect and Affection to her, and their own Concern at her departure.</p>
            <p>But <hi>as your Afflictions abound, God can make your Conſolations by Chriſt abound much more:</hi> And ſuch Loſſes as theſe, (though ſome of the ſmarteſt and moſt afflictive to humane Nature) may turn to your Spiritual Gain: And even <hi>this Rod,</hi> like that of <hi>Aaron,</hi> may bloſſom, and produce the <hi>peaceable Fruits of Righteouſneſs:</hi> If in the want of their Company, God himſelf be more depended on as <hi>your All in all:</hi> If their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval out of this World, promote your Mortification to it: if their being taken up to Heaven, aſſiſt your Preparations, and excite your deſires to follow: God hath already made good his Covenant Promiſe, in a very peculiar manner, to thoſe whom he <hi>gave,</hi> and hath <hi>taken</hi> from you; and I truſt will do ſo as to thoſe who remain: that they may <hi>know and ſerve the God of their Fathers with a perfect heart, and ſee the Felicity of his Choſen:</hi> That they may tread in the ſteps of their departed Relatives,
<pb facs="tcp:95216:3"/> and bear up the Name of God in their reſpective ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; to his Glory, and your Comfort, and their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. And if God ſhould not <hi>make your houſe to grow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2 5.</note> 
               <hi>yet he hath made an Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with you, well ordered in all things, and ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh the following Diſcourſe may contribute any thing to your Support: or at leaſt be accepted, as an Expreſſion of my Obedience in complying with your requeſt thus to make it publick: And as a Teſtimony of my unfeigned Reſpect to the <hi>memory</hi> of the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed:</hi> with a ſerious deſire of ſome benefit to others alſo, by ſuch a <hi>remarkable Inſtance</hi> of an <hi>Early Piety,</hi> of an <hi>Exemplary Life,</hi> of a <hi>peaceable Death:</hi> Which <hi>God grant,</hi> who alone can bring Good out of Evil; all whoſe Works are perfect, and whoſe Wayes are Judgment. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Affectionate Humble Servant, <hi>John Shower.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. <hi>25. 1681/2</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Being Earneſtly deſired, both by the <hi>Relations</hi> of the Deceaſed Gentlewoman, and by the <hi>Preacher</hi> of the following Funeral Sermon, to Teſtifie what I knew of the Gracious and wonderful workings of the holy Spirit upon the Heart of this Perſon during Her Life; I could not but yield to their Importunate requeſts.</p>
            <p>And upon this occaſion I muſt declare; That having Known her from her <hi>Childhood;</hi> and having very much obſerved her <hi>Converſation</hi> of late, and being called to give her ſeveral viſits in her <hi>ſickneſs,</hi> I do believe (upon the whole) that God did give her a <hi>ſound Repentance</hi> for, and a <hi>Full Remiſſion</hi> of all her ſins, through the mediation of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I can aſſure thee, <hi>Reader,</hi> who ever thou art: that ſhe had an awakened <hi>ſight of her ſins,</hi> accompanied with a great meaſure of <hi>Godly Sorrow</hi> for them; I diſcerned alſo in her a <hi>deep Humiliation,</hi> and I heard her open <hi>ſelf-Condemnation</hi> thereupon. I found in her alſo a clear Knowledge of the Nature of the New <hi>Covenant;</hi> together with a Right Apprehenſion of the Nature of that <hi>Faith,</hi> which is Required of all men (and is through Grace beſtowed upon ſome penitents) whereby the Soul doth attain to an Intereſt in that Covenant: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:95216:4"/> thereby, united unto Chriſt; and <hi>conſequently,</hi> doth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Benefits of his <hi>Merits:</hi> and doth receive the Fruits <hi>of his Attonement</hi> with the Inhabitation of his <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saving Faith and True Repentance are alwayes inſeparable; and their Conjunction doth evidence and <hi>ſpeak</hi> them to be true and ſaving: both Theſe (I do believe) were united in the Soul of this deceaſed perſon. And therefore I have very great Hopes of her State: All <hi>Faith</hi> which is pretended to, where <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> is wanting, I account to be nothing but a preſumptuous Confidence; and all ſeeming Repentance, which is not Accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſome Faith in the Divine Goodneſs, and in the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made thereof (by our Lord Jeſus) is no other than the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance <hi>of a Cain,</hi> or a <hi>Judas</hi> his deſpair.</p>
            <p>Our Lord Jeſus did (as it were) <hi>Epitomize</hi> the whole Goſpel, and <hi>comprehended</hi> the whole Duty of man in two words: <hi>viz. Repent and Believe:</hi> and 'tis to be obſerved; that theſe <hi>two</hi> are ſet in the very Front, as the Text to all his Miniſtry, <hi>Mark 1.15.</hi> And by <hi>reaſon</hi> of the Import of them, they may be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the Contents of the whole.</p>
            <p>Where theſe two Graces are not conjoyned, <hi>Guilt</hi> Remains, and <hi>Sin</hi> Reigns: But where they are united in any Soul, as that <hi>perſon</hi> is <hi>Juſtifyed,</hi> ſo that <hi>Heart</hi> is ſavingly changed; and that Nature is in meaſure <hi>Sanctified;</hi> and the life of that man (for the Future) will be proportionably, univerſally Holy. Would the Genius of the preſent Age allow me to uſe Metaphors in Soul-concernments; I ſhould think that I did then beſt explicate to vulgar capacities the nature of ſaving Faith: as when I did call <hi>Faith</hi> the <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of Knowledge, the <hi>Siſter</hi> of Repentance, and the <hi>Mother</hi> of Love; for the Holy Ghoſt tells us, that Faith comes in by <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> Ro. <hi>10.17.</hi> That it Purifies the Heart, Acts <hi>15.9.</hi> and works by Love, <hi>Gal. 5.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God had given this perſon, the True Seed of ſuch a Faith, was evident by it's <hi>Fruits:</hi> the Apoſtle tells us, that <hi>he</hi> that hath <hi>not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his,</hi> Ro. <hi>8.9.</hi> And alſo
<pb facs="tcp:95216:5"/> he tells us, that <hi>as many as are led by the Spirit are the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God,</hi> Ro. <hi>8.16.</hi> Now I muſt profeſs that (ſo far as I was able to Judge) I have ſeldom ſeen a dying perſon, manifeſt more of a Chriſt-like Spirit than ſhe did; That is, I never ſaw more of a Spirit <hi>Thirſting</hi> after communion with God, of a Spirit more <hi>contemning</hi> the World, of a Spirit more deeply <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> unto the will of God, or a Spirit more <hi>patient</hi> under the Croſs; and more <hi>Submitting</hi> to the Rod of God.</p>
            <p>Indeed I knew once a perſon, that did <hi>exceed</hi> her herein; and it was her Renowned Father: <hi>a man of the greateſt and moſt deſerved name,</hi> for Piety and Sincerity, for Humility and Patience, of all men, In or Near the City, that I have known: Who Feared no Pain or Torture upon any <hi>other</hi> account, but <hi>this</hi> only, <hi>viz.</hi> Leaſt they ſhould tempt him to the Leaſt <hi>unbecome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Groan, in ſome great paroxiſme of the Stone.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Submitting</hi> of our <hi>wills</hi> to divine will and <hi>pleaſure</hi> in all things, is the <hi>ſumme</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of all <hi>practical Religion</hi> here, and the full <hi>conforming</hi> of our <hi>wills</hi> to the divine <hi>will, and mind,</hi> is the <hi>height</hi> and <hi>Top</hi> of all mans <hi>Happineſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after:</hi> to enjoy <hi>this priviledge,</hi> of full conformity <hi>to God,</hi> is the Portion of <hi>None</hi> in this World; and to perform that <hi>Duty</hi> of ſubmiſſion to him, is the Attainment of but very <hi>Few;</hi> yet this deceaſed perſon was ſo great a Favourite, as that God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to beſtow <hi>this rare Jewel</hi> to be worn in her Boſom, who did ſeem with <hi>John</hi> to Lye very near the Heart of her Saviour.</p>
            <p>Very <hi>ſignal</hi> and <hi>Conſpicuous</hi> is the <hi>diſcriminatng</hi> Grace of God, towards <hi>ſome</hi> perſons more than towards <hi>others:</hi> 'tis true, that God is not <hi>wanting</hi> to the Happineſs of any of his Creatures: and his abſolute <hi>Sovereignty</hi> ſeems in all things to be governed by his Infinite goodneſs; ſo that, he is both Juſt, and good to all: yet there is nothing more <hi>notable,</hi> or more <hi>evident,</hi> than that there are ſome objects of his Love, who are his <hi>Segul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lahs;</hi> his peculiar ones: in whom God doth <hi>eſpecially</hi> delight; and unto whom God doth do good with his <hi>whole Heart,</hi> Jer. <hi>32.41.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:5"/>
            <p>As God doth ſuffer moſt men to make their own <hi>choice,</hi> and doth beſtow upon them what they do fully and Finally <hi>chooſe:</hi> ſo he will himſelf chooſe as he will, and he will do with his <hi>own gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitous favour</hi> as he himſelf pleaſeth; and he will give no account to <hi>any</hi> of his <hi>own</hi> matters.</p>
            <p>A great Inſtance hereof was this <hi>now</hi> bleſſed perſon, of whom I may ſay, that her <hi>whole Life</hi> was full of Gods <hi>goodneſs:</hi> and that <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> did follow her even all her <hi>daies;</hi> which <hi>daies,</hi> the favour of Heaven would not ſuffer to be <hi>many;</hi> becauſe it did ordain, that her <hi>Sorrows</hi> and her <hi>Temptations</hi> ſhould be but <hi>Few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time being nothing but a <hi>dreſſing Room</hi> to Eternity; the <hi>ſhorter</hi> it is, the <hi>ſooner</hi> do Holy Souls enter into the more <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate</hi> preſence of the Glorious Majeſty.</p>
            <p>It is Reckoned in holy Writ, as an act of <hi>very Great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> ſhewn by <hi>Hegai</hi> (the Kings Chamberlain) unto <hi>Eſther,</hi> that all things neceſſary for her <hi>Purification,</hi> and for her due <hi>preparation,</hi> for the love of her <hi>deſigned</hi> Husband <hi>(The great King Ahaſhuerus,)</hi> were given to her <hi>more ſpeedily</hi> than to others: whereby a <hi>Quicker</hi> acceſs to the King was afforded her; and the Crown was ſo much the <hi>ſooner</hi> ſet upon her Head.</p>
            <p>The good Spirit of God did deal <hi>ſomething</hi> after the ſame manner, with this <hi>young Virgin:</hi> For the work of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was <hi>haſtened</hi> in her, that ſhe might the more <hi>early</hi> receive the Crown of Glory, from the <hi>King of Kings:</hi> and might be preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed holy and without ſpot, or blemiſh, or wrinkle or any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Few pages, and fewer hours allotted me for this work, will not permit me to enumerate the many <hi>ſpecial</hi> favours that were <hi>ſhoured down</hi> upon this perſon <hi>while ſhe lived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not therefore take notice of the priviledges of her <hi>Birth,</hi> or the Honour of her <hi>Family,</hi> which were <hi>great;</hi> neither will I mention her Natural endowments, of <hi>parts,</hi> or <hi>Beauty,</hi> or any ſuch thing; Bleſſed be God, that ſhe her ſelf (though young) had learned <hi>before her death,</hi> to Reckon ſuch enjoyments as
<pb facs="tcp:95216:6"/> theſe, to be very <hi>mean</hi> and poor, when compared with the <hi>Joyes</hi> that were ſet before her.</p>
            <p>They are Love-tokens of a <hi>greater value,</hi> which I did obſerve to be conferred upon her; and theſe were <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſo many;</hi> That I may ſay that ſhe was one of thoſe that <hi>God had bleſſed with all ſpiritual bleſſings in heavenly things in Chriſt:</hi> and I may adde with the Apoſtle, that God <hi>having choſen her in him from before the Foundation of the world, to be holy and without Blame.</hi> And the ſame God having decreed the <hi>end,</hi> did alſo ordain the Means.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, in the <hi>Firſt place</hi> the kindneſs of God appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>ordering,</hi> that ſhe ſhould be <hi>born</hi> of, and <hi>brought up</hi> by very pious, and Religious Parents; and few perſons did ever enjoy more Spiritual <hi>Nurtriture,</hi> and <hi>Admonition,</hi> or had a greater ſtock of Prayers laid up for them, than this Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the reſt of that Offspring.</p>
            <p>Another ſingular Mercy, which did promote her Salvation, was the excellent <hi>pattern,</hi> of modeſty, vertue, and piety which was afforded her by her elder Siſters. The Influence of a <hi>Good example</hi> is alwaies greatly <hi>Advantagious:</hi> but when it is found in near <hi>Relations,</hi> 'tis much more obliging and efficacious.</p>
            <p>Another great Bleſſing, <hi>much conducing</hi> to her Eternal Happineſs, was this, that in her <hi>youth,</hi> ſhe enjoyed the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Attending upon <hi>ſuch an eminent Miniſtry;</hi> that the very <hi>Enemies</hi> thereof, have been heard to <hi>Confeſs,</hi> that it is very <hi>Learned,</hi> and moſt <hi>Rational,</hi> and <hi>further</hi> they know not: but ſuch as are <hi>Taught of God,</hi> and have their <hi>ſpiritual ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces exerciſed,</hi> ſo as to be acquainted, not only with the <hi>form of Godlineſs,</hi> but alſo with <hi>the power thereof,</hi> theſe men do ſay, that the Characters which the others do give of this emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſons teaching, are moſt true; and they do further alſo ſay, that it is <hi>extraordinary Clear</hi> and <hi>convincing, moſt Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical</hi> and <hi>Scriptural; greatly practical</hi> and <hi>profitable,</hi> and yet <hi>very Sublime</hi> and <hi>Spiritual.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:6"/>
            <p>Now Reader conſider, whether <hi>many (if any) ſuch</hi> have finally miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried; whoſe <hi>Natures</hi> were <hi>gentle,</hi> and eaſie to be <hi>entreated;</hi> whoſe <hi>hearts</hi> were <hi>Soft</hi> and <hi>Tender;</hi> who had the Benefits of ſuch <hi>Education,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Example;</hi> who enjoyed ſuch Teaching <hi>abroad,</hi> as well as ſuch Counſel at <hi>home;</hi> and all, accompanyed with <hi>ſervent Prayer</hi> unto God for a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> which I am ſure that ſhe did not want: it being reported of her Father, that his Cuſtom was (with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>119.164.) Seven times a day to pray unto the Lord, and to praiſe him.</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, I am informed, that this <hi>deceaſed Gentlewoman</hi> was obſerved to ſpend much time in <hi>Cloſet-Prayer</hi> of <hi>late;</hi> conſider then, I ſay, whether we may not <hi>hope confidently,</hi> that the Grace of God had <hi>ſavingly</hi> and <hi>effectually</hi> wrought upon her; who was both viſibly <hi>in Covenant</hi> with God; and whoſe heart alſo God had <hi>diſpoſed</hi> and <hi>prepared,</hi> by ſuch ſpecial Means of Grace which he had beſtowed upon her.</p>
            <p>And this is yet <hi>more evident,</hi> if we <hi>reflect</hi> upon Gods dealing with her in <hi>her laſt Sickneſs;</hi> whereby God did ſeem <hi>to ſeal Inſtruction</hi> deeply upon her Soul. Her diſtemper was one of the worſt ſort of Small Pox: At her firſt being taken, ſhe had ſtrong apprehenſions that ſhe ſhould dye; ſhe therefore did fall cloſely upon the work of <hi>Examination,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the aſſiſtance of ſome <hi>Miniſters</hi> therein; and ſhe was viſited by many: ſhe opened her caſe to us all, and God was pleaſed to make her to ſuſpect and be jealous of the worſt; and to confeſs, and condemn her ſelf for, her Sins, both of Omiſſion, as well as Commiſſion; and humbly to inquire after the <hi>only way</hi> of Pardon: And it pleaſed God ſo to bleſs theſe laſt helps, as that <hi>none</hi> of us, who viſited her, do doubt; but the ſame Spirit who <hi>convinced her of Sin and of Righteouſneſs,</hi> did at length <hi>ſeal her up to the day of Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Alpha,</hi> the firſt <hi>Beginning</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of all <hi>practical</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is <hi>that act</hi> whereby a Soul doth <hi>deliberately, reſolvedly, freely,</hi> and <hi>expreſſely dedicate</hi> and <hi>devote</hi> it ſelf unto <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Service:</hi> Thus the Saints in <hi>2 Cor. 8.5.</hi> The <hi>Omega,</hi> the <hi>laſt, concluding,</hi> and <hi>conſummating</hi> work of a devout Soul, is to <hi>commit</hi> and <hi>commend its Spirit into the hands of God, as to a faithful Creator:</hi> thus did <hi>Stephen, Acts 17.59.</hi> Yea thus did our Lord Jeſus himſelf: <hi>Luk. 23.46.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus alſo did this bleſſed Perſon: ſhe did, I hope, <hi>begin</hi> well, in an early <hi>Conſecration</hi> of her ſelf to God; I am ſure ſhe did <hi>end</hi> well: and 'tis the <hi>end that Crowns the work:</hi> ſhe did reckon, that ſhe had not fully <hi>Finiſhed her courſe;</hi> nor rightly laid the <hi>Top-ſtone</hi> of her <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Building,</hi> ſo as to cry <hi>Grace, Grace unto it;</hi> untill ſhe had moſt <hi>devoutly</hi> and <hi>humbly</hi> offered up her <hi>Soul</hi> to God in <hi>Prayer,</hi> by the aſſiſtance of ſome Friend and Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Accordingly, although it were <hi>midnight,</hi> and although my Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:95216:7"/> did ſend for me: and with the cleareſt uſe of her <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and the moſt fervent deſires of her <hi>Soul;</hi> ſhe did entreat me, that I would in her Name, <hi>ſolemnly</hi> and <hi>expreſſely ſurrender</hi> and <hi>Give up</hi> her Soul into the <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Boſom</hi> of her Saviour, in whoſe precious Blood, ſhe did <hi>hope,</hi> that all her ſins were <hi>now</hi> fully waſhed away.</p>
            <p>I did <hi>readily</hi> obey the Call, and did comply with her deſire: for I <hi>did,</hi> and <hi>do</hi> judge, that this deſire of hers proceeded from ſome <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Impulſe,</hi> and <hi>work of the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> And Reader, thou wilt think, as I doe, if thou ſhalt <hi>read</hi> and <hi>obſerve</hi> the <hi>effect</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence</hi> hereof; as it is related to thee, in the <hi>cloſe</hi> of the following diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Almoſt ſuch another <hi>extraordinary Impreſs</hi> (as it may be thought) was made upon her Spirit, on occaſion of this <hi>Author</hi>'s preſenting her with a <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> which he had preached but a little while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe was taken <hi>ſick:</hi> which Sermon ſhe having <hi>received,</hi> and <hi>read,</hi> and <hi>diligently conſidered;</hi> ſhe was heard to ſay, That ſhe did think, that <hi>her own change</hi> would not be <hi>far off;</hi> and that ſhe could <hi>wiſh,</hi> that the Author might preach <hi>her</hi> Funeral Sermon alſo: and ſhe then named the Text (now inſiſted upon;) and ſaid, That ſhe <hi>hoped,</hi> that God would make <hi>her Funeral Sermon</hi> as profitable <hi>to other</hi> young ones, as the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Sermon had been to <hi>her ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her Prognoſticks were <hi>too true,</hi> as to the <hi>ſhortneſs</hi> of the time which ſhe lived <hi>after</hi> thoſe words <hi>were ſpoken</hi> by her; God grant, that her <hi>hopes</hi> be not <hi>fruſtrated;</hi> but that all her <hi>dying words</hi> may prove truly <hi>Prophetical;</hi> and eſpecially thoſe, which related to the profitable <hi>ſucceſs</hi> of the Sermon here before thee.</p>
            <p>The Author hath done his part <hi>like himſelf,</hi> as well in <hi>this,</hi> as in the <hi>former Diſcourſe;</hi> Oh that he might find as <hi>diligent,</hi> and as <hi>conſidering Readers</hi> as ſhe was; many excellent Conſiderations, very <hi>ſubſervient,</hi> and <hi>conducing</hi> to thy Conviction and Salvation, are propoſed herein: but all will be in <hi>vain,</hi> and to no <hi>purpoſe,</hi> without thine <hi>own Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and the <hi>Spirits application:</hi> Concerning the Diſcourſe, I muſt ſay <hi>no more,</hi> and I can do <hi>no leſs;</hi> than to allude to the words of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Eccl. 12.9. And moreover, becauſe the Preacher was wiſe, therefore,</hi> in this Diſcourſe, <hi>he hath Taught the people Knowledge; and hath given good heed, and ſought and ſet in order many</hi> Arguments for thy preparing for <hi>Death,</hi> and moreover for <hi>preferring</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> before <hi>Life:</hi> The Lord convince thee by them; and alſo carry thee <hi>comfortably</hi> through all <hi>Time</hi> to <hi>Eternity.</hi> My Paper is ſhort, and my Time ſhorter, I muſt therefore conclude; for the Sermon is wholly Printed, and ſtops only untill I have told thee that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Friend and Souls Servant,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:7"/>
            <head>A <hi>Funeral Sermon:</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHIL. I. 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SAint <hi>Paul</hi> writing from <hi>Rome</hi> to the Church at <hi>Philippi,</hi> in this Chapter acquaints them with his Bonds and other Diſcouragements; which he tells them by their Prayers and the Aſſiſtance of the Spirit of Chriſt obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby,<note place="margin">V. 12.</note> would turn to his Salvation and the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">13.</note> and had already been attended with ſome conſiderable ſucceſs in that kind;<note place="margin">14.</note> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and confirm the Profeſſors of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">19.</note> and to propagate and promote <hi>it</hi> even in the Court of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and in other places; and if Chriſt might be magnified,<note place="margin">20.</note> he was perfectly indifferent to Live or Dye: <hi>For to me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95216:8"/> v.</hi> 21. His Life he hop'd might advance the Honour of Chriſt; and his Death would be ſubſervient to the ſame deſign: by his further ſervice if he live, and by his ſufferings if he dye; by his Miniſtry ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his Life, and by his Martyrdom in caſe of his death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">V. 22.</note>
               <hi>But if I live in the fleſh, this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is the fruit of my labour;</hi> or, it is worth my Labour to glorifie the Redeemer by continuing in this World. <hi>Yet what I ſhall chooſe I wot not. For I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To <hi>Depart</hi> or be diſſolv'd, the Original word is uſed both by Chriſtian and Heathen Writers for a departure from any place to return home.<note place="margin">Luk. 12.36</note> And when the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaks of his approaching death, he tells us,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 4.6.</note> that <hi>the Time of his departure was at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having a deſire</hi> to depart, a vehement and earneſt deſire, as the word imports; and <hi>to be with Chriſt,</hi> to be abſent from the Body,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 5.8.</note> and <hi>preſent with the Lord;</hi> with that merciful <hi>Saviour, who</hi> had compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on me, when as an ignorant Blaſphemer I perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted his Members; <hi>who</hi> call'd me to be an Apoſtle, and enabl'd me by his Grace to own his Truth in the face of Dangers, and hath hitherto comforted me in all my Tribulation. I deſire to depart, that I may be with <hi>him. With him,</hi> not with the <hi>bleſſed Angels</hi> or <hi>departed Saints,</hi> though their Society will make a part of the heavenly Joy: Not the <hi>former,</hi> they are but miniſtring Spirits and menial Servants imployed under him; and though they ſhine as Stars, yet <hi>he</hi> is the enlivening Sun, from whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their Luſtre and borrow all their glory. Not the <hi>latter;</hi> they have no Bleſſedneſs but by his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95216:8"/> and Purchaſe, no Crowns of Life but what <hi>he</hi> puts on. Therefore 'tis not to be with them only or chiefly, that made him thus groan to be diſſolv'd, thus earneſtly deſire to depart, but <hi>to be with Chriſt: Which is far better,</hi> ſimply and in it ſelf more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, <hi>by much more better,</hi> the Comparative being double in the Greek Text; and yet I wot not what to chooſe, for <hi>I am in a ſtrait betwixt two. On the one hand,</hi> his Love to the <hi>Philippians</hi> who needed his prefence, (many falſe Teachers being at that time crept in among them,<note place="margin">V. 24.</note>) made him willing to abide in the fleſh, and deferr his own felicity for a time upon their account: But the Glory of Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence <hi>on the other,</hi> and his own unſpeakable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by it, made him deſirous of a Departure; and therefore, though he determines for the <hi>former,</hi> and was content to Live, and 'tis probable had ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret intimation from Heaven, that all his work in this World was not yet finiſht; yet he grants the <hi>latter</hi> to be ſimply more eligible: <hi>having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far Better.</hi> Which words are not more ſuitable to a <hi>Funeral Solemnity,</hi> than expreſſive of the <hi>dying Thoughts and Temper of our deceaſed Friend,</hi> and were choſen by her as the Subject of my preſent Diſcourſe. And that I may comprehend the Subſtance and Deſign of the Text, according to the deſire of the Dead, for the Benefit and Inſtruction of the Living; let us conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When and how far it is warrantable for a Chriſtian to deſire death?</p>
            <p n="2">2. In what reſpects to depart and to be with Chriſt is far Better than to abide in the Fleſh.</p>
            <p n="3">3. On what Grounds and Principles a Chriſtian may expect a future Bleſſedneſs with Chriſt after
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95216:9"/> his departure, ſo as to encourage and excite his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires after it?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whence it comes to paſs, that even thoſe who acknowledge it Far Better to be with Chriſt, than to continue in the body, are yet unwilling to depart in order to it? and what Remedies are proper to the caſe of ſuch?</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Application of the whole, particularly with reſpect to the ſad Occaſion of our preſent Meeting.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When and how far is it warrantable for a Chriſtian to deſire to be diſſolv'd? This Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may be anſwered in the following Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our <hi>diſſolution</hi> and departure as a <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>penal evil,</hi> as contrary to Nature, or as the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sin, cannot poſſibly be the Object of a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional deſire: If God hath promiſed a long Life as the Encouragement and Reward of our Obedience, and threatned an haſty death as the puniſhment of Impiety: If it be univerſally true, that the Soul of man deſires Union with the Body, and unavoidably dreads a ſeparation from it: If Torturing pains and loathſom Diſeaſes are the uſual Antecedents of dying: If the Corruption of the Body, and its Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment in the Grave till the general Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be the certain Conſequent of our diſſolution: We cannot but think of Death as a <hi>natural Evil;</hi> and <hi>as ſuch</hi> decline and fear it.</p>
            <p>Much leſs deſirable will it appear, if conſidered as the <hi>Wages of Sin,</hi> and the Fruit of Gods diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the Juſt Sentence of his Vindictive Juſtice: but how far our diſſolution in this latter Notion of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95216:9"/> it is changed by the death of Chriſt in reference to Believers, is another queſtion, and will more properly be conſidered under the third Inquiry.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our diſſolution and departure ought not to be deſired, <hi>Only</hi> as a freedom from Temporal Evil; as preventive of preſent ſuffering, or delivering us from it. The Apoſtle doth not mention the uneaſie Circumſtances of a Priſon, or the continual hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to which he was expoſed from the malice of his adverſaries, as the ground of his deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, but <hi>to be with Chriſt:</hi> he knew very well that a Chriſtian may ſerve the ends of God's glory, and be uſeful to others in a ſtate of ſuffering: and therefore when he ſaith in another place, <hi>We that are in this Tabernacle do groan being burden'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.3.4.</note> he adds the limitation in the following words, <hi>not to be unclothed but cloth'd upon, that mortality may be ſwallowed up of Life:</hi> not meerly to avoid the inconveniencies of our abode in ſo poor a dwelling, but to come to the poſſeſſion of the <hi>building not made with hands eternal in the Heavens.</hi> Not meerly to find relief and deliverance from our preſent burdens,<note place="margin">Job 7.13 Jon. 4.3.</note> when through melancholy or diſcontent we are weary of Life: when we have ſet our Hearts on ſomewhat we cannot obtain, or ſtruggle with ſome difficulties we cannot maſter: or are impatient under bodily pains, or quite diſpirited by the ſad proſpect of approaching Calamities; in ſuch a caſe to wiſh for Death, and <hi>deſire to depart,</hi> is unbecoming the Character, the incouragement and hopes of a Souldier of Chriſt: much leſs will the Gallantry of a <hi>Roman</hi> or a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the deſire of Death, only to prevent Slavery, or avoid Diſgrace, or miſs the ſight of an unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95216:10"/> object. As <hi>Cato</hi> reſolv'd to dye that he might not behold <hi>Victorious Caeſar,</hi> whom by all means poſſible he had endeavoured to ruine:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icero in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſcul. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith expreſly of him, that the reaſon of his choice was juſt, and that <hi>Cato</hi> ought to dye rather then ſee the face of a Tyrant. But we have not ſo learn'd Chriſt, for</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt not deſignedly precipitate or haſten our own departure; nor wilfully neglect any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable means to preſerve our Lives, how deſirous ſo ever we are to be with Chriſt: we acknowldge <hi>God</hi> as the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Owner</hi> of our lives, and ſhall we preſume to diſpoſe of what is <hi>his,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a declaration of his conſent and order to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize us? Are we bound by the ſixth command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to preſerve the Life of our neighbour, and may we be negligent and careleſs of our own? is not every man nearer to himſelf than any other can be? and is not ſelf-murder a violation of the Law of nature and condemned by a general ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage? and can we ſuppoſe it a ſufficient Juſtification of our ſelves, that we profeſs a deſire to <hi>be with Chriſt?</hi> whereas we may not do this or any other evil, though the greateſt good may come of it: <hi>he that haſteth to be rich,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> even in this ſence, <hi>ſhall not be innocent.</hi> We muſt be intirely devoted to ſerve and glorifie the Redeemer as long as we live; and rather dye upon the Spot, than quit our Station without the order of our General: and yet we muſt not ſhipwrack our health, or expoſe our Lives to hazard, without a Warrant from Heaven.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A <hi>Sincere</hi> deſire to be with Chriſt is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with <hi>ſome fear</hi> of Death, and a reproveable <hi>unwillingneſs</hi> to depart and be <hi>diſſolv'd.</hi> The exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95216:10"/> of Chriſt himſelf is uſually urg'd in vindication of a natural ſenſitive fear of Death, <hi>viz.</hi> the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery thereof which he made by his Agony and prayer in the Garden. But a <hi>Socinian</hi> only will aſſert, that therefore he was more affected with the fear of Death than many of the Martyrs have been, becauſe of the exquiſite Temper and tender conſtitution of his body; and that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what was natural and ordinary in his caſe: whereas he was to conflict with the wrath of God, and bear the curſe, and be wounded for our Tranſgreſſions, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> otherwiſe his own innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and perfect reſignation to the will of his Father, and the proſpect and aſſurance of victory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, would certainly have prevented his Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble agony and bloody ſweat and importunate cries, <hi>that if poſſible the Cup might paſs from him.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I doubt not, but a Timerous Temper may render ſome perſons extreamly apprehenſive of the pains of death, and on that account unwilling to depart, though they are truly <hi>deſirous</hi> to be with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Others through the weakneſs of Faith or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much concern in the affairs of this Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though they grant it unſpeakably better to be preſent with the Lord, and have choſen it as their portion and final Happineſs; may yet be loth to paſſe through the dark valley: they cannot joyn with the Apoſtle in deſiring to be <hi>diſſolv'd,</hi> though they can ſpeak it from their very hearts, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to <hi>be with Chriſt;</hi> and that deſire is ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing as to keep them upright, and yet not effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious, ſo as to conquer the fears or interpoſing death. How unwelcome was the meſſage of Death
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95216:11"/> to an <hi>upright Hezekiah,</hi> even then when he could plead his Integrity before the Lord? <hi>he turn'd his face to the wall, and wept,</hi> and beſought the Lord that he might not dye, as is evident by <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.3, 5, <hi>v.</hi> compar'd: but I dare not ſay, his unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to dye at that Time was a ſinful weakneſs, becauſe he might well be concern'd for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom after his deceaſe, leaſt the faithful ſhould be ſtaggered, and the people revolt to Idolatry, there being no viſible <hi>Succeſſor</hi> to advance the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo hopefully begun; for <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was not then born, being but twelve years old when he began to reign, and we know that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had fifteen years added to his Life. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.6.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though we deſire to be with Chriſt, we muſt not be peremptory as to any <hi>determinate Time;</hi> but refer our ſelves to God's good pleaſure for the ſeaſon of our departure: though with <hi>Job</hi> we ſhould be <hi>ready to anſwer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 14.15</note> 
               <hi>when God doth call,</hi> yet with humility and reſignation we muſt expect his ſummons, and <hi>wait till our change come:</hi> though the <hi>daies of our appointed Time</hi> ſhould be longer than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary. Though in a dutifull obſervance to our Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father we ſhould be willing to return home as ſoon as he ſhall pleaſe to call us, and the felicity of his preſence ſhould render it deſirable; yet his Soveraign will and unerring wiſdom muſt be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically acknowledg'd in reference to the Seaſon: he alone, of whom and to whom are all things, is fit to determine how long we ſhall tarry, or how ſoon we ſhall depart: even the Light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may teach us this:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> Epiſt. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> And therefore, when ever we pray <hi>Thy Kingdom come,</hi> we muſt not limit the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> by preſcribing the <hi>Time;</hi> but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95216:11"/> immediately ſubjoyn, with reſpect to <hi>that, Thy will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Not the Time only, but the <hi>Kind and Manner,</hi> of our diſſolution muſt be referr'd to God. Some have wiſht for a ſudden death, and others have pray'd againſt it. Some have deſired to dye by one diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and others by another.</p>
            <p>Some holy perſons of a timerous Temper and a tender Body, would chooſe to depart by a <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> not only as allowing them a longer Time to prepare for death, but as an eaſier kind of Death than ſeveral others: Whereas, beſides the uncertainty and deceitfulneſs of that diſeaſe, 'tis more than poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that the Languiſhment of a pining ſickneſs may be as irkſome and inſupportable, as the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er pains of more violent diſtempers. But God is the only Judge (to whom we muſt Submit, as the wiſe diſpoſer of all events) not only of the Time but the Manner of our departure: not only how <hi>long</hi> we ſhall ſojourn in this earthly Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, but <hi>what</hi> ſhall diſſolve and pull it down.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Our <hi>deſire</hi> to depart and to be with Chriſt, muſt not be <hi>raſh and haſty;</hi> but the reſult of many Serious and deliberate thoughts, comparing both States together, and underſtanding the difference. The Apoſtle knew his duty in compliance with the Will of God, and therefore for the ſervice of his Maſter, and the advantage of the <hi>Philippians,</hi> was willing to Live: but he knew withall, it was far better in it ſelf to depart that he might be with Chriſt, and as ſuch he deſired it. And a due <hi>compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> between our preſent and our future Life, our inconveniencies and ſufferings in this world, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95216:12"/> our Felicity in the next, is proper to regulate and quicken our deſire to be abſent from the body, and preſent with the Lord. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In what reſpects is it far better to be with Chriſt, than to abide in the fleſh?</hi> what is the vaſt difference between <hi>What we are,</hi> and <hi>What we ſhall be?</hi> that the expectation of the <hi>Latter</hi> ſhould even make Death and diſſolution deſirable in order to it. And here it will be neceſſary to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Expreſſion of our Felicity after death here uſed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Being with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In <hi>what reſpects 'tis far better</hi> to depart, and be abſent from the body, that we may be preſent with him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Expreſſion of our <hi>future bleſſedneſs,</hi> by <hi>being with Chriſt.</hi> Till we are preſent with the Lord, and ſee him face to face, and know as we are known, we muſt content our ſelves with ſuch ſenſible repreſentations of <hi>it,</hi> as God is pleas'd to reveal in his Word; ſuch as our ignorant earthly minds can bear, and may be moſt affected with. But when once the vail of darkneſs is remov'd by death, we ſhall ſee him as he is, and all our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties be purified and inlarg'd, and ſuited to the bleſſed company and work above. We ſhall ſee <hi>him whom our Souls love,</hi> and reap a Happineſs by doing ſo, bigger than our preſent Hopes, and far above our higheſt Thoughts about it: For <hi>in his preſence is fulneſs of Joy, and at his right hand are Everlaſting pleaſures.</hi> And can we imagine, that a bleſſedneſs, purchas'd by infinite Merit, contriv'd by infinite Wiſdom, and prepar'd by infinite Power,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95216:12"/> and beſtow'd at length through infinite Grace, will in any thing be defective? Doth not our Apoſtle deſcribe it beſt, by aſſuring us it cannot be deſcrib'd; that 'tis greater than we ever ſaw, beyond what we ever heard, and far above what we can ever think? Doth not the very hopes of ſeeing him, revive our drooping hearts? Oh what will be the Glory of that bleſſed ſight! is not the pledge and aſſurance of it by the Harbinger of his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit exceeding comfortable? Oh what tranſcendent Satisfaction will his preſence give us! We now comfort our ſelves with the Contemplation, and one another with the Diſcourſe of it: and if our dark Faith and our faint Hopes, can give us ſuch a Joyful proſpect of what ſhall be conſequent to our diſſolution; into what raviſhing Joy ſhall we enter by the open Viſion and full enjoyment? Is the encouragement and ſupport of a Chriſtian now, from <hi>his preſence with us</hi> here; and will it not be far better to be <hi>preſent with him</hi> above, <hi>to be for ever with the Lord?</hi> When we ſhall never queſtion his Love to us, or doubt of ours to him, but have a full aſſurance of the one, and a glorious exerciſe of the other?</p>
            <p>And becauſe our knowledge will be ſtill increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, our flames of Love ſhall ſtill riſe higher. But what additional Bliſs the Soul ſhall have by the Reſurrection of the body, and the great Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Judgment Day, we know but in part. Bleſſed God, we know <hi>ſo much</hi> in this imperfect ſtate, <hi>enough</hi> to excite our deſires, and quicken our preparations, and encourage our Perſeverance. And let's bleſs him more, that he hath prepared <hi>ſuch a glory</hi> for us in the preſence of the Redeemer,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95216:13"/> as we cannot fully underſtand, till death convey us to him.</p>
            <p>But <hi>to be with Chriſt,</hi> is not only eligible in it ſelf, as expreſſive of our future Glory; but much rather to be deſired, if conſidered <hi>comparatively:</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In what reſpects</hi> is it preferrable to an abode in the fleſh, ſo as to make us rather chooſe to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,</hi> that we may be with him; than Continue in the Body, and be abſent from the Lord?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is not a ſtate of <hi>Reſt</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable, than to be continually harraſs'd with <hi>Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>Sorrow?</hi> We ordinarily begin this World in Tears, and ſolemnize our own Nativity as we do the Funerals of our deareſt Friends: as if we were <hi>then</hi> ſenſible of that univerſal Curſe which hath afflicted Mankind ſince the firſt Tranſgreſſion; and had a clear proſpect of the miſeries we are born to, and muſt afterward ſuffer: And in all the Portions of our little time, what and how many do we every where encounter! How many things are there which we find are wanting both as to our Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments and Enjoyments? and how much are we diſappointed, if we look for ſatisfaction from <hi>the luſts of the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.16</note> 
               <hi>the luſts of the eyes, and the pride of life? which,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>is all that is in the world:</hi> Earthly Pleaſures, Wealth and Honour.</p>
            <p>Do we not find, that what doth rejoyce and pleaſe us one day, appears with another Face when we view it next? or if we think it would pleaſe us ſtill, 'tis gone e're we are aware, and with all our skill and power we cannot protract its duration. Do not evil accidents overtake us on a ſudden, and our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95216:13"/> moſt probable deſigns miſcarry in the birth? as if all things were governed by Chance, and there were no Intelligent Director to overſee and regulate the Affairs of the World, and the Actions and Conditions of men: Inſomuch, <hi>that the Race is not to the ſwift,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>nor the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell to the ſtrong, nor Bread to the wiſe, nor Riches to men of underſtanding, nor Favour to men of skill, but Time and Chance happens to them all.</hi> Our Pleaſures flatter and deceive us, and our Afflictions trouble and diſquiet us: We are impoſed upon by our Senſes, and miſguided by our Paſſions: Croſs'd in our Deſires, and fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in our Hopes: griev'd by preſent evils, or perplext with the fears of future: and our Spirits for the moſt part diſcompos'd either by perſonal or relative Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. Some rueful Spectacle is ever now and then preſented before our Eyes; ſome evil tidings or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant ſound doth grate our Ears. We bewail the wants of the Poor, which we cannot ſupply; or envy the proſperity of the Wicked, which we cannot hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; or grieve at the Afflictions of the Righteous, which we cannot remedy.</p>
            <p>We have ſome ſuffering Friend with whom to ſympathize, ſome diſtreſſed or deceaſed Relation to lament: ſome unhappineſs of our own, or of thoſe we love, to be concern'd for. Beſides the Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and unfaithfulneſs of our ſeeming Friends; the Hatred and Malice of our open Enemies; the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Actions of profeſſing Chriſtians; their Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Animoſities among themſelves, and their deſpiteful uſage and entertainment from the World; the Complaints of the Miſerable, the Groans of the Sick, the Cries of the Oppreſſed, and our own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Infirmities, weakneſſes and pains, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> enough
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95216:14"/> one would think to make us defire to depart, and render us extreamly willing to lay down and dye, (if God think fit,) that we may be at reſt; eſpecially having the expectation of being <hi>for ever with the Lord.</hi> For otherwiſe even<note n="*" place="margin">M. Anton. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib. <hi>3. 4.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rr. Epict. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</hi> Boeth Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ul. Philoſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Heathens have ſpoken excellently of the Advantages of Death, as the period of our preſent Sorrows.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is not a ſtate of <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>perfect purity,</hi> far better than a Life of <hi>Temptation, Corruption</hi> and <hi>Sin?</hi> How are we now buffeted by <hi>Satan?</hi> by his Sinful ſuggeſtions, his ſubtil devices and ſnares, and his fiery darts? and by that means our Integrity aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, our peace of Conſcience unſettled, and our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance indangered?</p>
            <p>Our Conflict with him is ſo difficult, and the iſſue of the battel as to what depends on us, ſo very uncertain; that we are often ready to throw down our Arms, and give up all as Loſt. For though he be a conquer'd and baffled Adverſary, through the victory which our Captain hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd againſt him; yet we cannot now Triumph over him, as hereafter we ſhall. And is it not far better to abandon <hi>this world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. 4.4. Eph. 2.</note> 
               <hi>of which he is the God,</hi> and get above that <hi>Air of which he is the Prince,</hi> that we may be with Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Moreover, how doth our depraved Nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually caſt forth mire and dirt? what remaining filthineſs is there yet to be purg'd? what power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts to be mortified and ſubdued? which indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us for Spiritual duties, and derive a damp and deadneſs upon all our Religious Exerciſes; which cool our Zeal, and abate the fervor of our Spirits in the ſervice of our Redeemer; which weaken our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95216:14"/> Confidence in Prayer, and ſhame our faces before the Lord in ſecret. And is it not far better to part with the body of fleſh, that thereby we may be rid of <hi>this body of ſin and death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.2</note> and be like our Saviour in perfect purity?</p>
            <p>Do we not complain of our Ignorance of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truths, and the bleſſed Myſteries of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, notwithſtanding all our means of knowledge? of our Earthlineſs and unbelief? of unbecoming Thoughts of God and holy things? of proud Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations and carnal reaſonings againſt his Works and Word? of languiſhing and imperfect Graces to be recovered and perfected, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> And is it not better be with Chriſt, where that which is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſhall be done away?</p>
            <p>Is not God diſhonor'd and provok't, by our fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Omiſſions and ſlight Performances of duty? do we not reſiſt and quench and ſadden his holy Spirit? and are we not often griev'd by God's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes and frowns? by the wounds and ſmart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grets of our own Conſcience? ſo that we <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber God and are troubled,</hi> and cry out in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Souls, <hi>Hath he forgotten to be gracious, and will he be merciful no more?</hi> Are not our holy Purpoſes inconſtant, and our beſt Reſolutions waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and unſteddy, and very quickly, very eaſily ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd by the breath of a ſmall Temptation?</p>
            <p>Have we not a conſtant Watch to keep over our Hearts and wayes? a perpetual War to manage with the Infernal Trinity, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil? and do we know his rage, and malice, and ſerpentine policy, with the Multitude, Strength and Power of his Temptations? How often we have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95216:15"/> been foil'd already, and how ſoon we may be ſo again? and ſhall we not be deſirous of a ſinleſs ſtate in the preſence of Chriſt; where no Tempter, no Temptation ſhall ever be admitted?</p>
            <p>Yea, had we no corruption or Sin of our own to be delivered from, yet our concern at God's diſhonour by the ſins of others, ſhould make us willing to depart; as much more deſirable than our abode on <hi>earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 24.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 24.4.</note> Which <hi>is given into the hands of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and defiled by its Inhabitants:</hi> Where the very Air is infected with Oaths and Blaſphemies, prophane diſcourſe and filthy Talk: Where the very Being of a God is queſtion'd, his Providence denyed, and his Authority mock't: Where the Goſpel of Chriſt is diſparag'd and deſpiſed, his Laws contradicted, his Worſhip polluted, his Inſtitutions ſubverted, and his holy Name made a cloak for Licentiouſneſs, and his faithful Servants trampl'd on by the foot of Pride, and ſcorned by men at eaſe, and forc't to own his Truth with the peril of their Lives. And can we ſay, It is good to be here? or is it not far better to forſake ſuch a Place and Company, that we may be with Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us conſider what are <hi>the grounds and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples by which a Chriſtian is aſſured of this Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the preſence of Chriſt after his diſſolution.</hi> This Inquiry is neceſſary, becauſe the diſcourſe of our future Bliſs with Chriſt cannot be ſuppoſed to have any effect or influence upon us, to make us deſire our departure, while we disbelieve or make a doubt of the matter.</p>
            <p>I hope it were needleſs to prove the Poſſibility of the Souls exiſtence in a ſtate of ſeperation from the Body.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95216:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether in the body or out of the body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>2.</note> would not have been a doubt to this great Apoſtle, if he could not poſſibly have liv'd but <hi>in it:</hi> neither could he deſire to depart that he might <hi>be with Chriſt,</hi> if after his departure he ſhould <hi>not be at all.</hi> And ſuppoſing the exiſtence of the Soul notwithſtanding the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Body, we have as full an aſſurance as the nature of the thing is capable of, that holy Souls ſhall be preſent with the Lord in glory, when ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the body: 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the Text hath a ſpecial relation to Chriſt and to be with him, is the Bleſſedneſs on the account whereof 'tis deſirable to depart; I ſhall only mention <hi>his Death</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> as a ſufficient ground to confirm our Faith in the certainty of being with him, and to excite our Deſires of a departure in order to it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Death of Chriſt.</hi> He hath cancell'd the Hand-writing againſt us, and put away Sin,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.7.</note> which is the ſting of Death, by the Death of the Croſs: a <hi>way is now open for us into the holy of holies by his blood,</hi> not for our Prayers only but our Perſons.<note place="margin">Heb. 10.19</note> He hath wounded the Head of the old Serpent, even by permitting him to bruiſe his Heel, by cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying his humane Nature, (which was only <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigium Deitatis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 23 21. Heb. 2.15</note>) As <hi>Benaiah</hi> ſlew the <hi>Egyptian</hi> with his own Spear. Having <hi>deſtroyed death and him that had the power of it, and delivered thoſe who were all their Life time ſubject to bondage, through the fear of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath ſet his foot on the neck of this Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, diſarm'd it of it's weapon, and rob'd it of it's
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95216:16"/> ſting, and aboliſht the uglineſs and poyſon of it. He hath diſmounted <hi>Hell and Damnation from behind him who Sat on the Pale-horſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6.8.</note> Whether the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> were buryed in <hi>Calvary,</hi> where the <hi>ſecond</hi> was crucifyed, as ſome affirm, I need not enquire; we know that his Death was our Victory, and his Croſs may be our Triumph, ſince the Devil is conquered, and death Sanctified, and the Grave perfum'd by his burial, ſo that we need not be afraid to lodge in a Sepulchre where our Lord himſelf hath ſlept.</p>
            <p>Yea ſince the effuſion of his Blood, there is an amiable ruddineſs in the Face of death; for that which was the Inſtrument of Juſtice, is now the meſſenger of Peace and Joy, that which was the gate of Hell, is the way to Life. He hath brought <hi>ſweetneſs out of the Strong,</hi> and <hi>meat out of the Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.21.</note> and therefore Death as well as Life is reckon'd in the Inventory of the riches of the Saints. <hi>All things are yours,</hi> becauſe <hi>you are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>His Reſurrection</hi> and Exaltation; his riſing from the Dead not only diſcovers the poſſibility of our Reſurrection, and gives us a <hi>pledge and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of it, as declaring the ſufficiency and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his Sacrifice;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.11. Iſ. 26.19.</note> that therefore the Dead in Chriſt ſhall live, and with his Dead Body ariſe: But being punctually effected according to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction and promiſe, it confirms the Truth of all his Word, and ſeals the promiſe of eternal Life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Believers. He hath open'd the Priſon doors, and loos'd the bands of Death,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> and roll'd away the heavy Stone from the Graves of his people; he is now become the <hi>firſt fruits of them that Sleep
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95216:16"/> in Jeſus:</hi> And <hi>hath the Keyes of Death and Hell;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1.</note> even the two moſt formidable enemies are under <hi>his</hi> Dominion: <hi>who though once he were dead, doth now live, yea live for evermore.</hi> And for this very end did God raiſe him up,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> that <hi>our faith and hope might be in him,</hi> in reference to the Bleſſedneſs of another Life.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſaith the Apoſtle, concerning that,<note place="margin">Act. 13.3</note> 
               <hi>he raiſed him from the dead, no more to ſee corruption. God ſaid, I will give you the ſure mercies of David;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 55.3</note> or an Everlaſting Covenant, which Death ſhall not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve: and his being riſen is the ground of our Faith and Hope that the promiſe ſhall be fulfill'd. For the Reſurrection of Chriſt is the evidence of the validity and Efficacy of his Death and Sacrifice, and a ſufficient proof, that his Precious Blood ſhed upon the Croſs,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> was the <hi>blood of an Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> Eſtabliſhing a Covenant of Grace, and making it truly Everlaſting; for we know that <hi>he is a Prieſt for ever, after the Power of an endleſs Life.</hi> And therefore <hi>know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to our unſpeakable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, Incouragement and Joy, <hi>in whom we have believed, and that he is able to keep unto that day, what we have committed to him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 12. Phil. 1. Jude 2. Col. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>to perfect what he hath begun; and at laſt preſent us blameleſs before the preſence of his glory with exceeding Joy. For our Life being hid with him in God,</hi> we are fully aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>that when he who is our Life ſhall appear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.</note> 
               <hi>we ſhall appear with him in glory; and becauſe he lives, we ſhall live alſo; and when</hi> he ſhall appear, we ſhall be <hi>like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Let us conſider, <hi>Whence it comes to paſs, that notwithſtanding the Bleſſedneſs of being with Chriſt, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95216:17"/> our aſſurance of it by his Death and Reſurrection, that yet we are ſo backward and unwilling to depart? What is the true reaſon why ſo many of thoſe who acknowledge it far better to be with Chriſt,</hi> yet cannot ſay with the Apoſtle, That <hi>they deſire to be diſſolv'd, that they may be with him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The weakneſs of Faith concerning the Inviſible World, and the future Glory of the Saints,</hi> is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why ſo many Chriſtians are unwilling to dye. They are very ſenſible of the inconveniencies of their preſent abode; they complain to God and men of Corruption, Temptation and Sin, and they hear of a bleſſed Deliverance from all theſe by Death, and a perfect Felicity in the preſence of the Redeemer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their diſſolution; but <hi>unbelief makes them ſtagger at the Promiſe:</hi> They are not fully ſatisfied that ſuch a tranſcendent Glory will be Conſequent to Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Did they but ſoundly believe the Teſtimony and Revelation which God hath given in his Word concerning it, they would chooſe to be <hi>abſent from the body.</hi> Some of the Ignorant Heathens have been deſperate in their Choice of death, only as the Period of preſent Calamities: but others who were doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Conſequence, have yet entertained it with an hearty Welcome: As <hi>Socrates</hi> for inſtance, who profeſs'd, That <hi>he ought not to fear death becauſe he could not tell whether it were good or evil:</hi> And ſhall not we who underſtand the Grounds and Principles, the greatneſs and certainty of a future Bleſſedneſs after Death, be as willing to depart? <hi>A confirmed Faith</hi> is therefore neceſſary and adviſeable in the preſent caſe: and the rather, that thereby we may <hi>quench the fiery darts of Satan;</hi> who if he cannot
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95216:17"/> hinder us of our Crown, would rob us of our Joyful Proſpect of it: if he cannot prevent our future Glory, would render us dejected in our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage thither: if he cannot prevail to exclude and baniſh us for ever from the Preſence of Chriſt, would darken our preſent comfort by the deſire and Hope of it: but more eſpecially at the proſpect and <hi>approach of Death,</hi> for <hi>that is his hour, and the power of darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by <hi>this ſhield of Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.11.16.</note> we may be able to ſtand even in <hi>that evil day</hi> of our diſſolution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Pains of Death.</hi> They pray that God would haſten his Glorious Kingdom, and bring them to it; and believe it to be moſt eligible to be with Chriſt; yet are loth their own Prayers ſhould be anſwered, and the end and object of their Faith obtain'd, through the diſcouraging apprehenſions they admit of a dying hour.</p>
            <p>Would we not be with the Lord, and know him better, and Love him more, and enjoy him fully? and ſhall we ſtick at <hi>a little pain,</hi> as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troductory to ſo great a Happineſs? A Pain that will ſpeedily convey us to Eternal eaſe and reſt; which thouſands of Holy Souls in Glory have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd more of, than we can fear.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe the Agonies of Death are ne're ſo frightful to Fleſh and Blood, <hi>hath not Our Redeemer a Rod and Staff to comfort us in the dark Valley?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 23.4.</note> Doth he not know what it is to dye, and how much we dread it? doth he not underſtand our weakneſs, remember our frailty, pity our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and bid us ask for ſupport and Strength?<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.2</note> yea hath he not promis'd, that <hi>when Heart and Fleſh ſhall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95216:18"/> fail,</hi> that <hi>he will be the Strength of our Hearts, and our Portion for ever?</hi> Shall Ignorant hopeleſs <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> without God in this world, without the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of being with Chriſt in the next, be ſo deſirous of Immortality, as to diſpatch themſelves, and be their own Executioners, to force an eſcape from the Body? and ſhall we reſiſt and ſtruggle, draw back and fear, object and be unwilling, when our Saviour calls us to endleſs and unſpeakable Felicity? Is not this the laſt Experiment of our Faith, and Patience, and holy Reſolution? the laſt eſſay of our Chriſtian Courage? Are not the antecedent pains of dying the fruit of ſin, no leſs than the throws and pangs of Travelling Women? and are the Latter tolerable in hopes of Children and their own deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance; and may we not ſupport the Former by the aſſiſtance of a greater and better Hope? Are they at all conſiderable and worthy our fear, if put in the ballance with the promiſed Salvation to follow on our departure? Are they comparable in the nature <hi>of evil,</hi> to the bleſſed Life they lead us to in the nature <hi>of good?</hi> or comparable to the gripes of Conſcience which unpardon'd ſinners meet with in Life and Death? yea do we not think them greater, and make them worſe by our foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh fears, than moſt do find them? Is not the ſting of Death remov'd, and the Heavenly Manſions prepar'd and promis'd? and is it a reaſonable requeſt, that God ſhould vary from his ſettled courſe and fixed Law, upon our Sole account? will nothing elſe content and pleaſe us, but that Heaven muſt deſcend to Earth, or we be in a moment tranſlated thither; to prevent our pain, and ſuperſede the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95216:18"/> of our diſſolution, which we fear will be ſo attended?</p>
            <p>As a proper Remedy in the preſent caſe, let us familiarize the Thoughts of Death by frequent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Meditation. Let us view it oftner in our way, that it may not meet us with ſo much Terror at our Journeys end. Let us admit the Thoughts of a departure with particular application to our ſelves, and improve the Funerals of our Friends as a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>memento</hi> that our own is near. Let us lay open the Picture of Death naked to our view, and urge it to our Hearts, with the Infinite Glory that immediately ſucceeds, and take in the Death and Promiſe of Chriſt, as our aſſurance of it. And this will reconcile us more to a Departure, and help to overcome our unreaſonable fears of pain and ſickneſs antecedent to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The weakneſs and declenſion of our Love to Chriſt,</hi> is another ground of our unwillingneſs to depart and to be with him. To a degenerate Soul, that is deſtitute of the Love of Chriſt, an <hi>Everlaſting diſtance</hi> would be more deſirable than a <hi>Local Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</hi> For <hi>that</hi> could not make him happy, he would ſtill be as far remov'd from Bliſs by being with the Lord, as the Center of a Milſtone in the bottom of the Sea would be from moiſture. But the company and converſe of thoſe we Love, muſt needs be eligible: and the more we Love them, the ſtronger ſtill will be our deſire of being with them; and the more impatient ſhall we be of every delay. And is it not the ſence and ſecret lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of our Hearts, <hi>Whom have we in Heaven but Chriſt?</hi> And are we not deſirous to forſake this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95216:19"/> Earth to enjoy his preſence? Certainly the growth, and ſtrength, and exerciſe of Holy Love to Chriſt, would even render our diſſolution grateful in order to it; and make our Hearts rejoyce at the approach of Death, <hi>as it did old Jacobs, to ſee the Waggons</hi> that are ſent to fetch us to our <hi>beloved Jeſus, who is Lord of that Country whither we are going.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Immoderate Love to this preſent World, and our Temporal Life.</hi> Were we crucifyed to fleſhly Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and ſenſual Joyes, to worldly Honours and earthly Riches; we ſhould leſs regret the thoughts of dying, and more heartily deſire <hi>to be with Chriſt.</hi> For as the pangs of Death are not ordinarily ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and intolerable to one whoſe ſtrength is waſted by a pining Sickneſs, as to him who is arreſted ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly in his full ſtrength and vigour; ſo will he more eaſily leave this World, who for ſome time paſt hath been dying to it.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.14.</note> Were we more <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed to the World, and the World to us by the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> we ſhould not ſo affectionately hug the Carkaſs of a dead Enemy, whom we our ſelves have crucifyed and ſlain; but wait for the Time, and long for the happy hour when we ſhall leave it, and be gone to our Eternal Reſt. Let us therefore make uſe of all the Chriſtian methods of Mortification, and look on this world as a ſtrange place, and our ſelves as <hi>Pilgrims and Strangers</hi> here; as Exiles from our own Country, and haſtening to it: And we cannot but wiſh our ſelves at home, and deſire a departure as neceſſary thereto; and in the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim ſigh to think of the vaſt diſproportion and difference between the ſlender entertainments of our Inn, and the plentiful Proviſions of our Father's houſe.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:95216:19"/>5. <hi>Blotted Evidences, and the want of Aſſurance,</hi> concerning our Title to the Heavenly Glory. And this we all pretend as the reaſon of our unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to dye: A <hi>Sadducee</hi> is loth to dye, leaſt he ſhould not be at all; an unprepared ſinner, for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing miſerable; and a doubting Chriſtian, becauſe he knows not whether Happineſs or Miſery ſhall be his portion after his departure. For were we well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red we ſhould be with Chriſt for ever, we could not be ſo backward and unwilling to be diſſolv'd. Had we any better grounds to hope, that ſin was pardon'd, and God our Covenant Father; that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven would be our Inheritance, and we ſhould not come into Condemnation; we might rejoyce to think of our departure, when and how it ſhall pleaſe God to call us. When the Pſalmiſt could ſay, <hi>The Lord is my Shepherd;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 23 4, 6</note> he could boldly venture upon death, and walk through the valley of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>without fear of evil:</hi> But when diſtreſs had brought his ſin to remembrance, and made him doubt of his condition, he cries,<note place="margin">Pſ. 39.13.</note> 
               <hi>Oh ſpare me a little longer, that I may recover ſtrength, before I go hence, and be no more ſeen.</hi> Could you ſay with the Spouſe of Chriſt in the <hi>Canticles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 6.3</note> 
               <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am his;</hi> you might chearfully joyn your <hi>Amen,</hi> when you hear the Spirit and the Bride ſay in the <hi>Revelations, Come Lord Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 20.2</note> 
               <hi>Come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore Try your State, and examine your ſelves afreſh; and endeavour with your utmoſt care and diligence to obtain a well grounded Aſſurance; founded on the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, by comparing the Promiſes of Remiſſion and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95216:20"/> Life with the requiſite qualifications and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of them. For <hi>if our hearts condemn us not, we ſhall have confidence towards God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3.21</note> even in a dying hour. To which end, let us endeavour by daily acts of Repentance to obtain a daily pardon. Let us ſumme up our accounts at the foot of every page; I mean reflect every Night on the paſſages of the preceding Day: That we may reſt on our Beds with the ſence of a daily pardon; and be as fit to dye, as we are to ſleep.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Our fond affections to our Friends on Earth,</hi> may make us loth to dye, though we hope to be with Chriſt in Heaven. But is not his Boſom more deſirable, than the arms and embraces of our deareſt Friends and neareſt Relations? muſt we not aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and <hi>hate them all for his ſake?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14.26</note> i. e. uſe them as contemptible and hated things, if they keep us from him. Have we not ſolemnly engag'd to do ſo, by our Covenant with God? and ſhall we not ſtand to our agreement? Is there no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>our Friends on Earth,</hi> and our <hi>beloved Saviour?</hi> How often is an unactive pity vouchſafed in the room of ſuccour; when <hi>they</hi> need our aſſiſtance, or <hi>we</hi> intercede for theirs! We know if they are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy,</hi> they ſhall forever be baniſht from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt; and we may well be aſham'd to be unwilling to dye on their account: and if they are <hi>holy,</hi> though we ſhall not return to them, yet we know that they ſhall ſhortly come to us. And cannot God inſtruct them in his fear, order their Conditions, diſpoſe of their affairs, provide for their comfort, and anſwer all our prayers in reference to them, after our departure? yea hath he not often done ſo?</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:95216:20"/>
            <p>Have we any Friends on Earth, that are every way ſo accompliſht, as alway to delight and pleaſe us? or are we ſo perfectly wiſe and good, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to diſguſt and diſoblige them? Is there not ſome ſelfiſhneſs, deſign, and private intereſt; ſome hypocryſie, flattery, and diſſimulation; ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality, unſuitableneſs, or inconſtancy in our friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips here? Are not the beſt of thoſe we love, Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and miſtaken, erroneous, deceiv'd, weak and impotent: and as likely to defile and grieve us by their Corruption, as to edifie and rejoyce us by their Grace? but hereafter, when that which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect is done away, they ſhall all have ſuitable qualifications to recommend them to our moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and conſtant Affection, and be every way more fit for our Content and Joy. We ſhall then be never weary of each others company: we ſhall fully underſtand one anothers mind: we ſhall live in perfect harmony, and full Satisfaction; without the dread of Abſence or fear of Separation. Now if we have ſome Friends, we have many Enemies; but in the preſence of Chriſt there ſhall be none but Friends, and ſuch as ſhall for ever be ſo: their Perſons being more amiable, and their Society more deſirable than now it can be. Now if we are pleaſed with their Converſe, we may quickly loſe it,<note place="margin">Exek. 24.16.</note> and the <hi>deſire of our eyes be taken from us</hi> by a ſudden ſtroke; that we know not how to value or uſe them, till 'tis too late. And ſhall we be unwilling, <hi>on their account,</hi> to depart and be with Chriſt? ſince they are haſtning after us, and after a few daies abſence we ſhall meet them again, and dwell with them for ever.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95216:21"/>5. The <hi>Application</hi> remains, which ſhall be only in four particulars, as <hi>Inferences</hi> from what hath been ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may hence take notice of <hi>the great Effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Power of the Chriſtian Faith and Hope.</hi> That notwithſtanding our fondneſs and affection to the Body, and the contrariety of death to our ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Inclinations; that yet this Faith and Hope can urge us to deſire a diſſolution in order to it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may hence inferr, that <hi>the Soul doth not ſleep in the grave with it's companion the Body untill the Reſurrection;</hi> but immediately paſs into a ſtate of bliſs. For the Apoſtle to abide in the fleſh, was more expedient for the <hi>Philipians; for him to Live,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 21.</note> 
               <hi>would be Chriſt,</hi> i. e. For the advancement of his glory; how then was it <hi>better to depart?</hi> or in what <hi>ſtrait</hi> could he be, whether he ſhould chooſe a longer Life, or a preſent departure; if no Bleſſedneſs were expected till the final Judgment? And why doth he mention his <hi>being with Chriſt,</hi> as that which made death deſirable? Is not the preſence of Chriſt with us on Earth, and our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ends of his Glory in this world, much more eligible than to Sleep in the grave till <hi>dooms day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Is it better to depart, and be with Chriſt, than abide in the Body? then the Fable of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> is hereby exploded. Were we to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by our diſſolution, only from Leſſer pains to Greater, or from a Life of Sorrow to a ſtate of Suffering, (ſuch as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> imagine their Purgatory to be, equivalent to the Torments of Hell in the extremity of them, though different in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95216:21"/> duration:) How were it far better to depart, that we may be with Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is it the object of a Chriſtians deſire to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and be with Chriſt? and is that far better than to continue in the body? Then <hi>let us not Grieve immoderately at the departure of thoſe, who have obtain'd their wiſh, and enjoy their deſire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did they long to be with Chriſt, and chooſe to be diſſolv'd in order to it? and is it their unſpeakable Satisfaction that they are ſo? and do we expreſs our Love and Kindneſs to them, by repining at their Felicity? ſhall their deſired Repoſe, and Reſt, and Happineſs; be our Torment, Grief, and Sorrow? would we, that contrary to their own welground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Inclinations, they ſhould continue longer here on Earth, or return back again from Heaven, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to gratifie our fond Affections? Have they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd a ſpeedy Victory after a ſhort Conflict; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the Crown of Life as ſoon almoſt as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun their Chriſtian race; the glorious recompence of Reward, though they had wrought but one hour in the Vineyard, when others muſt Labour twelve? and ſhall we mourn like utter Strangers to the Chriſtan Faith and Hope? Would we delay the Glory of God in their Salvation, and deferr their Felicity in the bleſſed preſence of the Redeemer; and be content that a Voice ſhould be wanting in the Heavenly Quire, rather than we be Sadned by their departure?</p>
            <p>Would Parents have their Children continue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in their Swadling-cloaths; or when advanc'd to riper years, wiſh them back again to Infancy, and hinder their poſſeſſion of that Inheritance,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95216:22"/> which they are born to, and diſpos'd to enter on and enjoy?</p>
            <p>Are not you your ſelves haſtening to the Grave, and Hope e're long to be with Chriſt? and is it not a refreſhing Thought, to conſider, that your <hi>Treaſure</hi> is there before you; <hi>with their Father and your Father, with their God and Saviour and yours;</hi> I mean your Holy Children and Friends whom you dearly Love?</p>
            <p>The Primitive Church was wont to Solemnize the Funerals of Holy Perſons, with ſinging Pſalms and Hymns of Praiſe to God, for their deliverance and felicity obtain'd by dying: And ſhall we refuſe to be comforted, for the death of thoſe who ſleep in Jeſus, and deſired to do ſo; <hi>as if in this Life only we had Hope in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Something 'tis true, of Grief and Sorrow muſt be allow'd to Nature, Duty, Cuſtom, and contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Friendſhip, and the Honour of the deceas'd: for they are reckon'd to dye miſerable, who are hurl'd into the Grave without the attendance of a Sigh, or Tear, or Funeral Lamentation. But our aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the future Glory they poſſeſs with Chriſt, (which they themſelves preferr'd to a longer abode on Earth) ſhould wipe our Eyes, and prevent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. We mourn that they are gone, and deſire their company; but we know, they do not wiſh themſelves back again for the ſake of ours; no, they are gone to better Friends above, than thoſe they have left below. And were it not for the weakneſs of our Faith and Hope, in reference to the inviſible world; were it not for the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power of unmortified Selfiſhneſs, and our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95216:22"/> Love of this preſent Life; were it not for the remiſneſs of our Love to Chriſt, and the bleſſed Saints; we could not but deſire to be with <hi>them,</hi> rather than wiſh that they ſhould be longer with <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore inſtead of an intemperate Mourning at their departure, let us imitate their Examples, and propound their holy Lives and Deaths as our Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern and Encouragement.</p>
            <div type="account_of_life">
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 1.</hi> SInce the Honour of <hi>Gods Grace</hi> may be very much advanced by our taking notice of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and power of it in Believers: Since to praiſe and imitate the holy actions of our <hi>departed Friends,</hi> is the only Communion we can now have with them; and their <hi>Example,</hi> though they are dead, <hi>may yet ſpeak</hi> to the Inſtruction and comfort of the Living; I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with ſome brief Account of that <hi>Excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> whoſe deceaſe gave occaſion to our preſent Meeting.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 2.</hi> And knowing the uſual <hi>Flattery</hi> of Funeral Orations, I ſhall paſs over the Advantages of her <hi>Birth,</hi> the Credit of her <hi>Family,</hi> the Sweetneſs of her <hi>Temper,</hi> (the beſt Soyl for the Fruits of the Spirit;) and the many other natural and acquired <hi>Accompliſhments,</hi> which rendred her <hi>Amiable</hi> to all that knew her; and only mention ſome Paſſages, that may either magnifie the Grace of God, or be proper for our imitation and encouragement: And therein ſhall deliver nothing, but either upon my own knowledge, or from the particular Account I have received from her <hi>neareſt Relations,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:95216:23"/> and thoſe Reverend <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who aſſiſted with their Prayers and Counſel during her Sickneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 3.</hi> Through the Bleſſing of God on a <hi>pious Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and other means of Grace, and in anſwer to the fervent Prayers of her <hi>holy Parents,</hi> for the fulfilling of God's <hi>Covenant Promiſe</hi> to them and to their ſeed; we have great reaſon to believe that ſhe had choſen the Favour of God as her Felicity and End, almoſt as ſoon as ſhe was capable of making a deliberate choice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 4.</hi> And a Life of <hi>Seventeen years,</hi> (whereof ſo great a part is loſt by Infancy and Childhood) is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly very ſhort for the growth and ripening of ſuch fruits of the Spirit as ſhe diſcover'd. <hi>A Time and Age,</hi> when Vice and Vanity are wont to bloſſom and ſprout forth in others. When the Thoughts of Death and Judgment are uſually rejected as unwelcome Intruders before their Time; and ſerious preparation for it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to a reputed more Convenient Seaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 5.</hi> But before that Age, <hi>her diligent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful reading of the Holy Scripture, and valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it above other Books,</hi> was very admirable and exemplary. Making this Bread of Life her daily food, and taſting ſuch ſweetneſs, and reaping ſuch benefit by it, that even <hi>at midnight,</hi> while others ſlept, ſhe would often ſpend ſeveral hours in reading the Bible: La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting on her death-bed the Loſs of Time by other Books; which could not aſſiſt her to a better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of her duty, and the mind of God, or take off her Affections from the Love of this World, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare her Soul for the Heavenly Glory.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:95216:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 6.</hi> Notwithſtanding this ſecret ſerious Piety, her <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> and <hi>Modeſty</hi> was ſuch, as not to make a great noiſe and ſhow to others, as if the Form of Godlineſs were the principal or only thing to be regarded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 7.</hi> For ſeveral weeks <hi>before her laſt Sickneſs,</hi> ſhe was obſerv'd leſs to regard the World than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; more Seriouſly to be devoted to God; and more to diſlike vain Company, and idle Talk, eſpecially if it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with it a Tendency and deſign to diſparage others: and in all reſpects ſo to demean her ſelf, as if ſhe had receiv'd ſome ſecret Revelation from God, that her Time would be but ſhort, and her change was near.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 8.</hi> Though before ſhe fell ſick, ſhe was fearfull enough of that<note n="*" place="margin">The ſmall Pox.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſeaſe,</hi> whereof ſhe dyed, yet having taken her Bed, and knowing the Diſtemper, ſhe profeſt her ſelf intirely willing to acquieſce in the will of God. And was diſpleas'd with any who would have tamper'd with her Face, or diſcours'd to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 9.</hi> Yea during the whole three weeks of her Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhe continued in ſuch a frame; notwithſtanding the loathſomeneſs of the Diſeaſe; notwithſtanding the Troubleſome Preſcriptions of Phyſitians; notwithſtanding her own <hi>Pains,</hi> of which, her Conſtitution, Breeding and Age conſidered, ſhe could not but be very apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive. And with an <hi>admirable Patience and reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the will of God,</hi> with a great contempt of the Vanities of this World, and an holy Indifference even to Life it ſelf, ſhe <hi>deſired to Depart:</hi> And that not meerly to be eas'd of her Pain, but <hi>to be with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95216:24"/> Chriſt,</hi> and the bleſſed Society above: or to uſe her own words, <hi>To be with her Heavenly and her Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Father:</hi> And gave this excellent reaſon for her deſire; Leaſt if reſtored to health, ſhe ſhould meet with ſome <hi>prevailing Temptations,</hi> that might turn away her Heart from God and Heaven: and therefore ſhe had rather be with Chriſt than put it to the Venture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 10.</hi> Her <hi>Victory over this World</hi> was likewiſe evident by the particular charge ſhe gave to thoſe about her, to let ſome <hi>young Gentlewomen</hi> of her Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance know from her, how Contemptible the beſt of this World will be, when they come to dye: and entreat them in her Name, (as her laſt requeſt, and the Expreſſion of her ſpecial kindneſs to their Souls) that they would not overvalue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 11.</hi> As an inſtance of her <hi>ſubmiſſion to the good pleaſure of God,</hi> and ſatisfaction in his order: ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, that her <hi>Mother,</hi> and the whole Family might joyn with her in ſinging the latter part of the <hi>39</hi> Pſalm: <hi>I was dumb,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>and opened not my mouth, becauſe Lord thou didſt it. When thou with rebukes doſt correct man for iniquity, thou makeſt his beauty to conſume away like a Moth. Surely every man is Vanity.</hi> Selah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which ſhe repeated by heart ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Metre.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 12.</hi> As an inſtance of her <hi>joyful Hope of Glory</hi> in the preſence of Chriſt after death, ſhe made thoſe who attended in her Sickneſs, frequently to read over the <hi>1 Theſſ. 4.</hi> cap. in the cloſe whereof, the glorious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Chriſt to Judgment is ſet forth; and the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95216:24"/> Happineſs of the Saints deſcrib'd,<note place="margin">Ver. 17, 18</note> by <hi>being ever with the Lord;</hi> with this addition, <hi>Wherefore comfort one another with theſe words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 13.</hi> With the free <hi>uſe of her Reaſon,</hi> to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laſt, God was pleas'd to give her the great Bleſſing of a <hi>Tender Conſcience;</hi> and therefore ſhe did not ſlightly overlook even <hi>little Failings</hi> without a penitent obſervation: and ſome of them ſuch as no man in a judgment of Charity would reckon ſinfull. Every thing that look'd like <hi>undutifulneſs to her Mother,</hi> ſhe hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily begg'd her Pardon for; though nothing conſiderable of that kind can be remembred to make her need for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs: thankfully owning the ſtrictneſs of her Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the ſeaſonable Reproofs of a diſcreet Parent, and even the abridgement of that Liberty which other young perſons take, (very often to their prejudice and ruine) as a ſingular advantage and favour from Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 14.</hi> In ſome part of her Sickneſs, ſhe had ſome humble becoming <hi>doubts and fears</hi> of her own ſtate; but having imparted them to a Reverend Perſon well acquainted in the Family, and heard his Reſolutions and Anſwers; ſhe was better ſatisfied, and expreſt her hopes of Pardon and Salvation through the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; <hi>who loved her and waſhed her from her Sins in his own Blood.</hi> Yea ſo far was ſhe from que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning the goodneſs of God, and the truth of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; ſo far from doubting of the alſufficiency of Chriſts Mediation, the Merit of his Sacrifice, and his willingneſs to receive returning Sinners: that the believing thoughts of it were her greateſt ſupport and joy; ſaying often in the time of her Sickneſs, That <hi>though her ſins were
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95216:25"/> as Scarlet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>God could make them Snow: though red like Crimſon, they ſhould be as Wooll.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 15.</hi> Moreover, ſhe did <hi>thankfully acknowledge the Mercies of God</hi> to her in the former part of her Life: whereof ſhe had very many, both Perſonal and Relative. And particularly deſired, that Thanks might be returned to God for his ſingular goodneſs to her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her Sickneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 16.</hi> She was <hi>very deſirous of Prayer to God</hi> on her behalf; and very joyfull and well pleaſed when ſhe had it: and being at any time ask't what particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar requeſt ſhe deſired ſhould be made to God for her: ſhe mention'd not her Recovery and the lengthening of her days; but the <hi>forgiveneſs of Sin</hi> through the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of her Redeemer; an humble ſubmiſſion to Gods diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal; and a prepared heart to acquieſce in his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſo in one ſence ſhe was <hi>full of dayes,</hi> though ſhe dyed very young: being ſatiated with the Time ſhe had liv'd on Earth; and not importunate for a longer ſtay.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 17.</hi> Within a few hours before her diſſolution, (of the approach whereof ſhe was more apprehenſive than thoſe about her) ſhe was very deſirous that a <hi>worthy Miniſter</hi> whom ſhe named,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> S. F.</note> might immediately be ſent for, to commend her Soul to God: Who accordingly came, though at Midnight. She her ſelf joyn'd in that laſt Office with great ſeriouſneſs and affection; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward return'd him her hearty thanks for his great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein, ſaying, <hi>Now I have nothing more to do, but to dye:</hi> Only requeſted him not to leave the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95216:25"/> houſe that night, as knowing, that his <hi>Company</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> might adminiſter to the <hi>ſupport of her Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate Mother,</hi> and other Relations, whom ſhe ſhould leave in ſorrow, though ſhe her ſelf was paſſing to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 18.</hi> After which ſhe compoſed her ſelf to reſt, and refuſed every thing that was offer'd her to take, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Signs with her hand, of her unwillingneſs to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 19.</hi> In that ſhort ſpace of her Continuance, which was not an hour, ſhe was heard to ſay, <hi>Be gone, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan! Be gone! Thou art a Lyar from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the Father of Lyes. O come Lord Jeſus.</hi> And ſoon after ſhe ſaid, <hi>He is Come, he is Come:</hi> And ſo fell aſleep, as in the Arms of her dearest Saviour, or as the Jews Report of <hi>Moſes,</hi> That he dyed with the Kiſs of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Death! where is now thy Sting? O Grave! where is now thy Victory? The ſting of Death is Sin, and the ſtrength of Sin is the Law: But thanks be to God, who hath given us the Victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And <hi>Bleſſed are the Dead, that Thus dye in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>§. 20.</hi> Would to God, that the Account here given, might effectually convince us, of the great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Death of the Holy and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholy, of the Righteous and the Sinner: Might convince us, of the great Bleſſing of <hi>holy Parents,</hi> and a good Education; and encourage Parents to be diligent and faithful, to be ſerious, prudent and affectionate, in the Education of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95216:26"/> their Children; becauſe ſuch a deportment is most like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be owned by God with the deſired Succeſs.</p>
               <p>And Convince us likewiſe of the <hi>Vanity of Youth,</hi> the ſhortneſs of our Lives, the uncertainty of our Time, the nearneſs of our Change, the neceſſity, reaſonableneſs and manifold advantages of <hi>Remembring our Creator in our younger Years:</hi> And withall might haſten our Preparations, and ſpirit our Deſires to depart and be diſſolv'd, whenever God ſhall call us. <hi>That following their Example who by Faith and Patience are gone to inherit the Promiſes,</hi> We may at length meet thoſe Precious Souls above, who are gone before us; that with them, and all the Children of the Kingdom, we may <hi>be for ever with the Lord,</hi> which is Best of all.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95216:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
